{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "In India,the state with highest density of population is",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Bihar ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Haryana ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn India,the state with highest density of Population is Bihar. Bihar with 1,106 population persons per sq. km. is most thickly populated state followed by West Bengal (1,028) and Kerala (860). ",
            "keyString": "762066s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the data released in July 2011, Sex Ratio in Rural Areas is less than urban areas",
            "optionA": "  Five Times ",
            "optionB": "  Four Times ",
            "optionC": "  Three Times ",
            "optionD": "  Two Times ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Census 2011. Female sex ratio in ruralIndia is 947 but in Urban areas it falls to 926. ",
            "keyString": "762283s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the census 2011, what is the density in India?",
            "optionA": "  325 ",
            "optionB": "  352 ",
            "optionC": "  372 ",
            "optionD": "  382 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe population density of India has risen to 382 persons square km. In 2001 the figure was 325. ",
            "keyString": "762425s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Approximately what percentage of world's cattle population is to be found in India?",
            "optionA": "  50% ",
            "optionB": "  18% ",
            "optionC": "  80% ",
            "optionD": "  7% ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tApproximately 18% of world's cattle population is to be found in India. ",
            "keyString": "762543s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to the figures of Census 2011,which state has the maximum difference in the male\nand female literacy",
            "optionA": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala ",
            "optionC": "   Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tState - Female literacy rate - Male literacyrate Rajasthan - 52.66%- 80.51% Kerala- 91.98%- 96.02% U.P.- 59.26%- 79.24% M.P.- 60.02%- 78.73% ",
            "keyString": "763189s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the following states, the literacy rate is highest in",
            "optionA": "  Odisha ",
            "optionB": "  Punjab ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Mizoram ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the given options the literacy of the following states are- 1. Odisha - 72.87% 2. Punjab - 75.84% 3. Maharastra - 82.34% 4. Mizoram - 91.33%",
            "keyString": "800565s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following states has the lowest literacy rate?",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Bihar ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBihar has the lowest literacy rate in India. It is about 61.80% according to census 2011 report. ",
            "keyString": "800718s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The 'Todas' are one of the major tribes found in",
            "optionA": "  Sikkim ",
            "optionB": "  Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Nilgiris ",
            "optionD": "  The Andaman and Nicobar Islands ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 'Todas' are one of the major tribes found in Nilgiris. One of the most primitive tribe of the Nilgiris is Todas. Toda people are a Dravidian ethnic group who live in the Nilgiri Mountains of Tamil Nadu.",
            "keyString": "800751s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the following States, ________ has the lowest birth rate in India.",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Bihar ",
            "optionD": "  West Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the census 2011 , Kerala has the lowest birth rate in India and recent survey also shows that there is decline in the crude birth rate (CBR) in Kerala (14.7) according to 2013 survey. ",
            "keyString": "800769s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the following, which State has highest level of literacy?",
            "optionA": "  Mizoram ",
            "optionB": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMizoram State has highest level of literacy. Literacy rate in Mizoram has seen upward trend and is 91.33% as per 2011 population census. Of that, male literacy stands at 93.35% while female literacy is at 89.27%. ",
            "keyString": "845945s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most literate union territory in India is",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Lakshadweep ",
            "optionC": "  Chandigarh ",
            "optionD": "  Puducerry ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the Census of 2011 the litereacy rate in Lakshadweep is 91.85%. Male literacy rate is 95.56% while for female it is 87.95%. ",
            "keyString": "845981s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  The Mahakaal Temple - Ujjain ",
            "optionB": "  Sringeri Matha  -  Chikkmanglur district ",
            "optionC": "  The Sun Temple - Konark ",
            "optionD": "  Jain Temples - Khajuraho ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Jain temples were built by Vastapul Tejpal, a Jain laymen between the 11th and 13th centuries A.D. and are world famous for thier stunning use of marble. These temples are situated over Mount Abu hills. Mount Abu is the only hill station in Rajasthan. ",
            "keyString": "845998s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs of states and tribes is not correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Assam: Miri ",
            "optionB": "  Nagaland : Konyak ",
            "optionC": "  Arunachal Pradesh : Apatani ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Pradesh : Lambada ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadhya Pradesh tribes and tribal culture information. Information about Central India Tribes like Gonds, Baiga, Bhil, Korku, Abujhmar, Bharia, Sahariya. ",
            "keyString": "846012s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kuki is related to which state",
            "optionA": "  Nagaland ",
            "optionB": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionC": "  Manipur ",
            "optionD": "  Tripura ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKuki tribe is an ethnic group spread over North eastern regions like Manipur and foothills of Chittagong hills. This tribe is mainly a follower of Christanity. ",
            "keyString": "846025s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the Census 2011, which state has the lowest population in India?",
            "optionA": "  Manipur ",
            "optionB": "  Tripura ",
            "optionC": "  Puducherry ",
            "optionD": "  Sikkim ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the Census of 2011 the population of Sikkim is 619,000 which is lowest in India. Sikkim is located at trijunction of India with China (Tibet), Nepal and Bhutan. ",
            "keyString": "903984s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to the data,released by housing and urban poverity alleviation ministry, which state has the maximum number of slums?",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Census 2011, Maharashtra has highest number of slum blocks in the Country. According to ministry reports out of 1 lakh slum blocks 21,000 lies in Maharashtra. ",
            "keyString": "904023s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After which one of the following tribes of India has a supercontinent of ancient geological history of the world been named?",
            "optionA": "  Santhals ",
            "optionB": "  Khonds ",
            "optionC": "  Bhils ",
            "optionD": "  Gonds ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter Gonds tribes of India has a supercontinent of ancient geological history of the world been named. The Gond people are Adivasi (indigenous people) of India that speak Dravidian languages and are listed as a Scheduled Tribe for the purpose of India's system of positive discrimination. The name \"Gondwana\" was proposed in 1872 by Medlicott from the ancient kingdom of the Gonds, one of the principal aboriginal tribes believed to have inhabited a large part of central India. ",
            "keyString": "904043s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which pair is not twin-cities?",
            "optionA": "  Durgapur - Asansol ",
            "optionB": "  Hyderabad - Secunderabad ",
            "optionC": "  Kolkata - Howrah ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi - New Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNew Delhi which is Indian capital is a territory inside Delhi. It is a part of big territory i.e. Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "904060s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian state with lowest sex ratio is",
            "optionA": "  Haryana ",
            "optionB": "   Punjab ",
            "optionC": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to census 2011 the sex ratio in Haryana is 879. Although government has claimed touch 950 mark. ",
            "keyString": "904076s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During which decade did the population record a negative growth rate?",
            "optionA": "  1921-31 ",
            "optionB": "  1911-21 ",
            "optionC": "  1941-51 ",
            "optionD": "  1931-41 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring 1911-21 the population record a negative growth rate. As per census 2011, Nagaland is the only Indian state which has negative growth rate of -0.58% in census 2011while Indian population grown at the rate of 17.69% from 2001 to 2011. ",
            "keyString": "960139s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There is no Scheduled Caste population in",
            "optionA": "  Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Nagaland ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Manipur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere is no Scheduled Caste population in Nagaland. Nagaland, Lakshwadeep and Andaman and Nicobar islands have no scheduled castes among their population. ",
            "keyString": "960178s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There is no Scheduled Tribe population in",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionC": "  Punjab ",
            "optionD": "  Rajasthan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere is no scheduled tribe population in Punjab. ",
            "keyString": "960196s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Child Sex Ratio as per the provisional results of the 2011 Census in India is",
            "optionA": "  927 ",
            "optionB": "  924 ",
            "optionC": "  917 ",
            "optionD": "  914 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the census 2011 child sex ratio has shown a decline from last census with 927 females per 1000 males. ",
            "keyString": "960213s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest population of Scheduled Tribes is in ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Sikkim ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe largest population of Scheduled Tribes is in Madhya Pradesh. Madhya Pradesh has the largest Tribal population. It has more than 1.6 crore Schedule Tribe population whom are 21% of state population according to 2011 census. ",
            "keyString": "960228s24m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following states the first synagogue is built in India?",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKerala has the 1st Synanogue built in India. Paradesi Synanogue is the oldest of the 7 Synanogue built by Jewish communities in Kerala. ",
            "keyString": "28142s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Khasi and Garo tribes mainly live in",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionC": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionD": "  Mizoram ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKhasi and Garo tribes mainly live in Meghalaya. The state of Meghalaya comprises Khasi, Garo and Jaintia hills. The scheduled tribe populations (mainly belonging to khasi, Jaintia and Garo tribes) constitute 85.53% of the total population. ",
            "keyString": "28176s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Birth rate measures the birth during an year per",
            "optionA": "  100 populace ",
            "optionB": "  1000 populace ",
            "optionC": "  10000 populace ",
            "optionD": "  100000 populace ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Birth rate measures the birth during an year per 1000 populace. A birth rate can be best described as number of live births per thousand of population per year. ",
            "keyString": "28192s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which state of India has the largest percentage of poors?",
            "optionA": "  Bihar ",
            "optionB": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "optionC": "  Orissa ",
            "optionD": "  Jharkhand ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per RBI estimates Chhattisgarh has highest poverty level with 39% people living Below Poverty line. ",
            "keyString": "28206s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Find the name of the state which has the lowest density?",
            "optionA": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionB": "   Mizoram ",
            "optionC": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Sikkim ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArunachal Pradesh with a population density of about 12 - 15 persons square per square km has the minimum population density. ",
            "keyString": "28218s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where are homogenous group \"Mangolab\" found in India?",
            "optionA": "  South-Region ",
            "optionB": "  Southern-Central Region ",
            "optionC": "  North-Western Region ",
            "optionD": "  North-East Region ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMangolabs migrated from China and Mangolia to Sikkim, Arunachal Pradesh and Nagaland, Manipur has a racial division including people of Central and eastern Asia. ",
            "keyString": "81250s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which state, female literacy rate is the highest?",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "   Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  West Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tState - Female literacy rate(%) Kerala - 91.98 Maharashtra - 75.48 Tamil Nadu - 73.86 West Bengal - 71.16",
            "keyString": "81295s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to the latest figures, literacy in India is",
            "optionA": "  63% ",
            "optionB": "  65% ",
            "optionC": "  67% ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording of census 2011, effective literacy rate has risen to 74.01% from 64.8% in 2011. ",
            "keyString": "81316s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where are Khasi and Garo tribes mainly found in",
            "optionA": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionB": "  Nagaland ",
            "optionC": "  Mizoram ",
            "optionD": "  Manipur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGaro and Khasi tribes are mainly found in hilly regions of Meghalaya. The dominance of these tribes is so profound that hills like Garo, Khasi and Jaintia are named after them.",
            "keyString": "81333s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India's biggest tribal group is",
            "optionA": "  Bhil ",
            "optionB": "  Gond ",
            "optionC": "  Santhal ",
            "optionD": "  Tharu ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to 2011 Census,Bhil is the most populous tribe having a population of 4,618,068 which is 37% of ST population. It is mainly found in Malwa region.",
            "keyString": "81349s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What percentage of Indian population is below poverty line?",
            "optionA": "  Less than 30 ",
            "optionB": "  30% to 35% ",
            "optionC": "  More than 35% but less than 40% ",
            "optionD": "  40% to 45% ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to official release of government of India in 2012. 22% of its population was below the poverty line. World Bank in 2011 estimated it to be 23.6%. ",
            "keyString": "171859s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to the census 2001,which was the largest state of India demographically?",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Bihar ",
            "optionC": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  West Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per the Census of 2011, Uttar Pradesh is demographically largest state of India with a population of about 20 Crores. ",
            "keyString": "172044s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the Stage in the population cycle in which India is classified on the basic of its\ndemographic characteristics?",
            "optionA": "  Early expanding stage ",
            "optionB": "  High stationary stage ",
            "optionC": "  Late expanding stage ",
            "optionD": "  Declinning Stage ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLate expanding stage is the 3rd stage of Demographic Transition. In this, both, the birth rate & the death rate fall, though population still rises but at much lower rate. ",
            "keyString": "172109s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Density of population in India is defined as",
            "optionA": "  Number of persons in an area of one mile square ",
            "optionB": "  Number of persons in an area of one lakh mile\nsquare ",
            "optionC": "  Number of persons inan area of one lakh km square ",
            "optionD": "  Number of persons in an area of one km square ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Density of population in India is defined as Number of persons in an area of one km square. No.of persons in an area of one Km. square population density can be defined as the number of persons in an area of one Km square. In 2011 population density has gone up to 382 persons per square km. ",
            "keyString": "172146s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which state amongst the following has the highest percentage of the Scheduled Caste population of State's population?",
            "optionA": "  Jharkhand ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Punjab ",
            "optionD": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per Census 2011, the State of Punjab, has the highest percentage of Scheduled Caste population amongst all the States of the Country.",
            "keyString": "172173s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the main reason behind the faster population growth in India",
            "optionA": "  Low Birth Rate and Low Mortality Rate ",
            "optionB": "  High Birth Rate and Low Mortality Rate ",
            "optionC": "  Faster Birth Rate and Faster Mortality Rate ",
            "optionD": "  High Birth Rate and High Mortality Rate ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main reason behind the faster population growth in India is High Birth Rate and Low Mortality Rate. Due to increased health facilities along with the development the mortality rates have gone down but still proper family planning has not been able to evolve leading to high birth rates. ",
            "keyString": "250967s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to census 2011, which union territory records the highest density?",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Chandigarh ",
            "optionC": "  Puducherry ",
            "optionD": "  West Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDelhi with an average increase of 20% of population every year and presently holding 11,297 persons per square km is most densly populated. ",
            "keyString": "251197s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is called the biggest leap forward in the history of Indian population?",
            "optionA": "  1921 - 1931 ",
            "optionB": "  1941 - 1951 ",
            "optionC": "  1951 - 1961 ",
            "optionD": "  1961 - 1971 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t1961 - 1971 is termed as the decade of population explosion or big leap forward as population went up drastically high. ",
            "keyString": "251368s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to the figure of census 2011, which of the union territories is last ranked in child sex ratio",
            "optionA": "   Dadar and Nagar Haveli ",
            "optionB": "  Daman and Diu ",
            "optionC": "  Chandigarh ",
            "optionD": "  Andaman and Nicobar Islands ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnion territory- Child sex ratio Dadar and Nagar Haveli -924 Daman and Div-909 Chandigarh -867 Andaman and Nicobar-966 Delhi-866 Lakshadweep-908 ",
            "keyString": "251562s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"This Union Territory possesses a coastal stretch of about 45 km with 28 marine fishing villages. However 45% of the population is engaged in agriculture and allied products\". Which among the Territories is referred passage?",
            "optionA": "  Lakshadweep ",
            "optionB": "  Pondicherry ",
            "optionC": "  Andaman and Nicobar ",
            "optionD": "  Daman ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis Union Territory possesses a coastal stretch of about 45 km with 28 marine fishing villages. However 45% of the population is engaged in agriculture and allied products. Lakshadweep among the Territories is referred passage. Lakshadweep is a tropical archipelago of 36 atolls and coral reefs in the Laccadive Sea, off the coast of Kerala, India. ",
            "keyString": "252074s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Growth rate of population means",
            "optionA": "  Difference between the growth of male and female ",
            "optionB": "  Difference between the population of urban\nand rural areas ",
            "optionC": "  No. of births per thousand persons ",
            "optionD": "  Difference between birth rate and death rate ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Growth rate of population means difference between birth rate and death rate. Population can be said to be growing when number of individuals increase in it. It can be best calculated by calculating difference between birth rate and death rate. ",
            "keyString": "327944s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements regarding literacy in India are correct ?\n1. A person who can only read but cannot write is not defined literate\n2. Children below 7 years of age are not taken into consideration even if they are able to read and write\n3. For the purpose of census, a person is deemed literate if he or she can read and write with understanding in any of the 22 languages mentioned in the Eighth Schedule of the Constitution\n4. The fact that a district has attained hundred percent literacy does not mean that the entire population in the district is literate",
            "optionA": "  1, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionB": "  2, 3 and 4 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following statements regarding literacy in India that are correct are: Children below 7 years of age are not taken into consideration even if they are able to read and write, For the purpose of census, a person is deemed literate if he or she can read and write with understanding in any of the 22 languages mentioned in the Eighth Schedule of the Constitution and The fact that a district has attained hundred percent literacy does not mean that the entire population in the district is literate. ",
            "keyString": "328135s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following religious groups in increasing order of their population in India:\n1. Muslims\n2. Buddhists\n3. Sikhs\n4. Jains\n5. Christians",
            "optionA": "  IV, II, III, V, I ",
            "optionB": "  IV, II, I, III, V ",
            "optionC": "  II, IV, III, V, I ",
            "optionD": "  II, III, IV, I,V ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following religious groups in increasing order of their population in India: Jains, Buddhists, Sikhs, Christians and Muslims. ",
            "keyString": "328303s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The tribal population in Andaman and Nicobar Islands belongs to the",
            "optionA": "  Astraloids ",
            "optionB": "  Caucasoids ",
            "optionC": "  Mongoloids ",
            "optionD": "  Negroids ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe tribal population in Andaman and Nicobar Islands belongs to the Negroids. Negroid is a grouping of human beings historically regarded as a biological taxon. The term has been used by forensic and physical anthropologists to refer to individuals and populations that share morphological and skeletal traits. ",
            "keyString": "328505s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In context of population, which of the following describes the correct meaning of \"Sex-Ratio\"",
            "optionA": "  Number of males per 1000 females ",
            "optionB": "  Number of females per 1000 males ",
            "optionC": "  Number of female per 1000 populace ",
            "optionD": "  Number of female per 1000 sample of persons ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSex ratio is used to describe the number of females per 1000 of males. As per census of 2011 sex ratio in India is 940. ",
            "keyString": "328694s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Indian state has the most no. of Scheduled Tribal population?",
            "optionA": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Bihar ",
            "optionD": "  Orissa ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMadhya Pradesh has the largest Tribal population. It has more than 1.6 crore Schedule Tribe population whom are 21% of state population according to 2011 census. ",
            "keyString": "388134s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to census 2001, the average annual growth rate during 1991 - 2001 is almost",
            "optionA": "  1.22% ",
            "optionB": "  1.93% ",
            "optionC": "  2.13% ",
            "optionD": "  2.24% ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Census 2011,the average annual growth rate during 2001 - 2011 estimated it to be 23.6%. ",
            "keyString": "388322s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the data released in July 2011, what is the percentage of population living in Indian villages?",
            "optionA": "  80% ",
            "optionB": "  75% ",
            "optionC": "  70% ",
            "optionD": "  60% ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Census 2011, approximately 83.3 crore people out of 121 crore population lives in villages which is nearly 70%. ",
            "keyString": "388517s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to census 2001, the highest density of population is in the state of",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Karnataka ",
            "optionC": "   Chhattisgarh ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to census 2001 Delhi was most densely populated state. In 2011 also Delhi has the density of 11297 persons per square Kilometre. ",
            "keyString": "388699s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is mainly responsible for the lack of female population in India?",
            "optionA": "  Political Factors ",
            "optionB": "  Economic Factors ",
            "optionC": "  Social Factors ",
            "optionD": "  Superstitions ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSocial factors are mainly responsible for the lack of female population in India. Social factors such as dowry and patriarchal mindset along with other prejudices are responsible for lack of population of females. ",
            "keyString": "388862s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India's population growth is characterized by",
            "optionA": "  An increase in rate of death ",
            "optionB": "  An increase in ratio of females ",
            "optionC": "  An increase in the birth rate and declining\ndeath rate ",
            "optionD": "  Increasing number of old people ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia's population growth is characterised by decadal (on every 10 year basis) growth of population on every census basis, which is based on an increase in the birth rate and decrease in death rate. ",
            "keyString": "463290s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the history of India population, which duration period is referred to as 'A great leap forward'?",
            "optionA": "  1921 - 1931 ",
            "optionB": "  1941 - 1951 ",
            "optionC": "  1951 - 1961 ",
            "optionD": "  1971 - 1981 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t'A great leap forward' in context of Indian population census in considered the decadal growth from 1951 to 1961. ",
            "keyString": "463327s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In general it is observed that the rate of population growth has been ________ in the densely populated areas compared to sparsely populated areas.",
            "optionA": "  Low ",
            "optionB": "  High ",
            "optionC": "  Negligible ",
            "optionD": "  Almost the same ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn general it is observed that the rate of population growth has been Low in the densely populated areas compared to sparsely populated areas.",
            "keyString": "463344s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The maximum percentage of the tribal population in India consists of",
            "optionA": "  Santhals ",
            "optionB": "  Bhils ",
            "optionC": "  Mundas ",
            "optionD": "  Nagas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe maximum percentage of the tribal population in India consists of Santhals. The Santal, or rarely Santals, are an ethnic group, native to Eastern South Asia, including India, Bangladesh, Nepal and Bhutan. Santals are the largest indigenous tribe in Jharkhand in terms of population, and are also found in the Indian states of Assam, West Bengal, Bihar and Odisha. They are the largest ethnic minority in northern Bangladesh's Rajshahi Division and Rangpur Division. ",
            "keyString": "463358s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Census data released on July 15,2011 reflects that 13.48% urban population lives in",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Bihar ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Rajasthan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs per census 2011, Maharashtra has 13.48% of urban population. About 70% of population of India lives in rural areas. Goa & Mizoram are 1st in terms of being urban whereas Himachal Pradesh has 90% rural population, the most in India. ",
            "keyString": "463371s25m32h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}